In the last video, we have set up our flesh asset for a coupled muscle and fat simulation.
지난 영상에서는 근육-지방 결합 시뮬레이션을 위해 Flesh 에셋을 준비했습니다.
Let's go ahead and set up our simulation parameters over here.
이제 여기서 시뮬레이션 파라미터를 설정해 보겠습니다.
First, let's go to asset details and then set your skeletal mesh, and in this case, want to use the bones here.
먼저 Asset Details로 가서 Skeletal Mesh를 지정하세요. 이번 예시는 이 본(bone) 세트를 사용합니다.
Again, at this point, you should make sure the underlying skeleton here in the skeletal mesh agrees with the one you used to set up the asset.
이 단계에서, 기반이 되는 스켈레탈 메시에 에셋을 만들 때 사용했던 메쉬와 동일한 것이 연결되어 있는지 꼭 확인하세요.
You can check the transform source and then check the name of the attribute.
Transform Source를 확인하고, 사용 중인 속성 이름도 체크합니다.
Here, you have the sk underscore email underscore muscles, which is that.
여기서는 ‘SK_Emil_Muscles’ 같은 근육용 스켈레탈 메쉬를 사용합니다.
Now, let's go to preview scene.
그다음 Preview Scene으로 이동합니다.
For a detailed explanation of the parameters, you can review the muscle simulation video.
각 파라미터에 대한 자세한 설명은 근육 시뮬레이션 영상에서 다시 확인할 수 있습니다.
Right now, we'll just quickly go through the parameters here.
지금은 여기 파라미터만 빠르게 훑어보겠습니다.
For this example, let's use 20 subsets and 20 iterations.
이번 예시는 서브스텝 20, 반복(iterations) 20을 사용하겠습니다.
Because this simulation has more layers than just the muscles, it contains the fat layer, which relies on the movement of the muscles.
이번 시뮬레이션은 근육만 있는 것이 아니라 지방층도 포함하고 있어서, 근육의 운동이 지방층으로 전달되어야 합니다.
And that means the deformation on the muscles need to propagate all the way to the fat layer.
즉, 근육에서 일어난 변형이 지방층까지 제대로 전파되어야 한다는 뜻이죠.
And that requires more solver iterations.
그래서 풀이 반복 횟수가 더 필요합니다.
Next, let's go ahead and check the quad aesthetics, because we're running a quad aesthetics simulation.
다음으로, 우리는 ‘쿼지정적(quasi-static)’ 시뮬레이션을 돌릴 것이므로 해당 옵션을 확인합니다.
Let's turn on fuller, for collision.
충돌 처리를 위해 관련 옵션을 켜줍니다.
And over here, we're going to use the Gauss-Seidel solver, because this is designed for quad aesthetics.
그리고 ‘가우스-자이델(Gauss–Seidel)’ 솔버를 사용합니다. 쿼지정적에 맞춰 설계된 솔버이기 때문입니다.
For now, we're turning off the spring collision.
지금은 스프링 충돌(Spring Collision)은 끄겠습니다.
Because the collision scenario is pretty complicated if you turn that on.
그 옵션을 켜면 충돌 경우의 수가 꽤 복잡해지기 때문입니다.
And that checks collisions against every single connected geometry group.
해당 옵션은 연결된 모든 지오메트리 그룹 간의 충돌을 전부 검사하게 됩니다.
We mostly want collisions between the outside of the fat layer only.
우리는 주로 지방층의 바깥쪽끼리만 충돌이 일어나길 원합니다.
For example, at the elbow.
예를 들면, 팔꿈치 부근처럼요.
We'll support this type of collision in the 5.6 release.
이런 형태의 충돌 지원은 5.6 릴리스에서 제공될 예정입니다.
So for now, let's skip that.
그러니 지금은 그 부분을 건너뛰겠습니다.
Let's turn off gravity, because that's currently incompatible with the Gauss-Seidel solver.
또한 중력은 끄겠습니다. 현재 가우스-자이델 솔버와는 호환되지 않습니다.
And make sure you have the do muscle activation on, so that the pain in muscles, the bicep, and the lower pectoralis can contract.
그리고 ‘Do Muscle Activation’ 옵션을 켜서 이두(biceps)와 하부 대흉근(lower pectoralis) 같은 근육이 실제로 수축하도록 합니다.
For this simulation, let's set the other animation, which is the range of motion animation.
이번 시뮬레이션에서는 다른 애니메이션으로 ‘관절 가동범위(ROM) 애니메이션’을 사용하겠습니다.
Coming down here, let's set a new cache collection.
여기 아래에서 새 캐시 컬렉션(Cache Collection)을 하나 만듭니다.
Let me name this one the fat chaos cache collection.
이름은 ‘Fat_Chaos_Cache_Collection’ 정도로 하겠습니다.
Let's run a little bit longer sim.
조금 더 긴 시뮬레이션을 돌려보죠.
Let's run 5 seconds at 30 frames per second.
30fps로 5초, 즉 총 150프레임을 실행합니다.
So 150 frames in total.
그래서 전체 프레임 수는 150프레임입니다.
So now let's hit that red record button to start a simulation.
빨간 ‘Record’ 버튼을 눌러 시뮬레이션을 시작합시다.
Once you hit that, the solver should start running in the background for some initial setups of the simulation.
누르면 솔버가 백그라운드에서 시뮬레이션 초기 설정을 수행하기 시작합니다.
And then you should be able to see a notification window soon.
곧 알림 창이 뜨는 것도 볼 수 있을 겁니다.
Because we have more vertices in the simulation, this should take more time in general.
이번엔 시뮬레이션 정점 수가 더 많아서 전체적으로 시간이 더 걸릴 겁니다.
And also we're using a higher number of sub steps and iterations.
또 서브스텝과 반복 횟수도 이전보다 높게 잡았습니다.
We'll wait for 2 frames to finish and then come back later.
프레임 2개 정도만 완료될 때까지 기다렸다가, 결과가 나오면 다시 보겠습니다.
The whole simulation took about 30 minutes to run, and we just got back the results.
전체 시뮬레이션은 약 30분 정도 걸렸고, 지금 결과가 나왔습니다.
Let's go ahead and hit play to start viewing the simulation.
재생(Play)을 눌러 시뮬레이션을 확인해 보죠.
Pay attention to the lower pectoralis there, as it's contracting with the arms coming down.
팔을 내릴 때 하부 대흉근이 수축하는 부분을 잘 봐 주세요.
Now that we have a simulation of the fat, let's transfer the deformation on the fat onto the skin.
이제 지방층의 시뮬레이션이 있으니, 그 변형을 피부(skin)에 전달하겠습니다.
Because that's what we'll see eventually.
결국 우리가 보게 되는 건 피부니까요.
We can embed the skin into the fat tetrahedral mesh,
피부 메쉬를 지방층의 사면체(tetrahedral) 메쉬 안으로 임베드한 뒤,
baryocentrically, and interpolate the skin from the simulation results.
바리센터릭(무게중심) 보간으로 시뮬레이션 결과에서 피부를 인터폴레이션합니다.
So let's go ahead and get back to the data photograph and create a new node called generate surface bindings.
그러려면 Dataflow 그래프로 돌아가 ‘Generate Surface Bindings’ 노드를 새로 만듭니다.
What this node does is that it takes either a static mesh or a skeletal mesh.
이 노드는 Static Mesh나 Skeletal Mesh를 입력으로 받을 수 있습니다.
Again, there is our skin, coarse, fixed, blend.
여기서는 우리의 피부 메쉬(예: skin_coarse_fixed_blend)를 쓰겠습니다.
And then we want to make sure that we connect that to the collection.
그리고 이 메쉬를 컬렉션과 연결해야 합니다.
So in this case, we want to embed it to the fat layer only.
이번 경우에는 지방층(fat layer)에만 임베드하면 됩니다.
So remember, we got the fat layer from here, get flesh asset.
‘Get Flesh Asset’에서 가져온 지방층 컬렉션을 사용하면 되죠.
So we can safely do it here.
여기서 안전하게 설정할 수 있습니다.
Now it's evaluating.
지금 평가(Evaluating)가 진행 중입니다.
It's finished.
완료되었습니다.
And then connect the collection back in.
이제 컬렉션을 다시 연결합니다.
Remember all the baryocentric data stored here,
여기에 저장된 모든 바리센터릭 데이터는
will be automatically updated through append tetrahedral collection.
Append Tetrahedral Collection을 통해 자동으로 갱신됩니다.
So eventually, you will have the right information on the appended collection.
결국 추가된 컬렉션에도 올바른 정보가 채워지게 됩니다.
In this node, there is also the option of do surface projection.
이 노드에는 ‘Do Surface Projection’ 옵션도 있습니다.
Remember, not all the time that the skin will be fully inside the fat layer.
피부가 항상 지방 사면체 메쉬 안에 완전히 들어가 있는 것은 아니기 때문입니다.
In this scenario that the skin is slightly outside of the tetrahedral mesh,
피부가 사면체 메쉬 바깥으로 약간 벗어나는 경우에는,
then we want to embed the skin onto the surface of the tetrahedral mesh and provide an offset.
피부를 사면체 메쉬의 표면에 임베드하고 오프셋 벡터를 적용해 주면 됩니다.
vector.
바로 그 오프셋 벡터입니다.
So make sure that you leave this on to embed those outside, slightly outside vertices.
그래서 피부 정점이 살짝 밖에 있어도 임베드되도록 이 옵션을 켜 두세요.
Now, with this set, we can go ahead and then set up the geometry cache generation.
이제 설정이 끝났으니 지오메트리 캐시 생성을 준비하겠습니다.
Over here, embedded skeletal mesh, make sure that this takes the same skeletal mesh as over here,
‘Embedded Skeletal Mesh’에는 앞에서 사용한 것과 동일한 스켈레탈 메쉬를 지정해야 합니다.
which is the skin.
즉, 피부 메쉬입니다.
Let's go ahead and set that.
그 값을 지정해 줍니다.
For geometry cache, let's go ahead and click this new geometry cache button and create a new geometry cache.
‘Geometry Cache’에서 새 지오메트리 캐시를 생성(Create)합니다.
Click save.
그리고 저장(Save)합니다.
Now that these two are set, we're ready to generate our geometry cache.
이 두 가지가 준비되었으니, 이제 지오메트리 캐시를 생성할 준비가 됐습니다.
Just click this button to generate geometry cache.
버튼을 눌러 지오메트리 캐시를 생성하세요.
Now that it's running.
생성이 시작되었습니다.
This should be much faster than the simulation because we're only reading the simulation results and interpolating the skin positions from that.
시뮬레이션 결과를 바탕으로 피부 위치만 보간하는 작업이기 때문에, 시뮬레이션 자체보다 훨씬 빠르게 끝납니다.
We can open up the geometry cache to view the results.
결과를 확인하려면 지오메트리 캐시를 열어보면 됩니다.
Let's go ahead and double click that.
더블 클릭해서 열어보죠.
There is our skin.
여기 피부 메쉬가 보입니다.
Then we can play and pay attention to that lower pectoralis there.
재생하면서 하부 대흉근 부분을 유심히 봐 주세요.
As you can see, the deformation from the fat layer is transferred onto that.
지방층에서 온 변형이 피부로 잘 전달된 것을 볼 수 있습니다.
And you can see some obvious muscle contraction on the skin now.
이제 피부 표면에서도 근육 수축이 뚜렷하게 보이죠.
So as a recap, we run a quasi-static simulation of the muscles and fat layer.
정리하면, 우리는 근육과 지방층에 대해 쿼지정적 시뮬레이션을 돌렸습니다.
We generated a geometry cache of the skin from the simulation results.
그리고 그 시뮬레이션 결과에서 피부 지오메트리 캐시를 생성했습니다.
In the next video, we'll use the geometry cache to train an ML deformer on the skin so that we can apply real-time correctives on the character skin with physics and biomechanics enhanced.
다음 영상에서는 이 지오메트리 캐시를 사용해 ML Deformer를 학습시키고, 물리와 생체역학을 반영한 피부 변형을 캐릭터에 적용해 보겠습니다.